of the 2012 London Olympics and welcome to the final of the women's 10 meter platform.
We had a rather edgy prelims, slightly better semi-final earlier today and hopefully we will be on course for an exemplary 10 meter final tonight.
Iulia Bogopchuk just getting in in 12th place.
All of these divers, including this lady in particular, looking to do a great deal better tonight.
Bronze medalist from last year at Paolo Sanchez.
Paolo Espinoza Sanchez.
She's built on the screen.
Naomi Batki of Italy will be after her.
And Hu Yu Dan.
Maybe somewhat surprised to see a Chinese diver so far down the pecking order.
Hasn't really gone into gear either in the prelims or in the semis, but she's in there, as indeed is Roslyn Finial.
With a much better semi-final than she did preliminary.
Christian Stewart has had a low degree of difficulty in her program, and it's worked to her benefit.
Doesn't always go for the big numbers, but she has been consistent, as has Julia Colton over.
of Russia.
Now onto the big hitters right at the top of the pile.
After both the prelims and the semi-final, Angela Pang, Melissa Wu, the two Americans, two Australians, I should say, together.
And they will be following one another in the competition tonight.
Very impressive was this young lady.
16 years of age.
On to the second ranked after the semi-final.
Make it Ben Fito, but you have to say head and shoulders and virtually all of a torso head of everybody else on the basis of what we saw this morning and indeed last night in the preliminaries is the top ranked of the Chinese defending champion.
Chen Ruolin.
Well, we're just about ready to go because the competition cannot start.
We can't get this party started without one very special addition to the guest list.
Leon Taylor.
Good evening, sir.
Thank you, Bob.
Well, there it is.
There is the 10-meter platform towering above all the other diving boards, very, very close to this ceiling.
And we have, finally, the final is here.
Now it's been, well, fair to middling, I would say, so far.
Generally speaking, the preliminaries were full of mishaps and mix-ups, and the semi-finals weren't actually much better.
So we finally got there.
We have 12 divers.
Each of the divers will perform five optional dives.
So these are the most difficult dives that these girls can perform.
total from each dive is obviously added to the next and to the next so it's a cumulative score decides the places and as Bob's already mentioned there is one person who is a cut above that is the Beijing Olympic champion at only 15 years old now she's the grand old age of 19 and she is well
miles in front.
She already qualified for the final after round four.
She did not even need to perform her last dive.
That is how good this young lady is.
There's Yu Yu Dan.
Now she is suffering.
I'm not sure whether she's injured.
No one seems to know, but she is off her game.
Heading into the hot tub there, the divers tend to pop in and out of that just to keep
the muscles warm in between dives obviously they dive in a sequence in an order and that order stays the same throughout there's pandanina i think that she could be on for a medal the 19 year old from malaysia nice outfit she's been looking really solid and she looks really relaxed there's the coaching corral keep them all penned in there as if they were sheep and some of them are britney probin there she's 16 from australia now if i was allowed to bet i'd be betting on this young lady for a medal
she is well come from strength to strength to strength.
There's Paola Espinosa way off the pace in the prelims and semi.
Now can she ride that Mexican high that they've been on in the diving pool?
Any question about the young Australian just going back to her Leon?
Round four dive.
I think on both occasions she's not dropped it exactly but she hasn't done it very well.
So one, two, three and five look great.
It's round four that could do for her.
Yep, well she's, well it could go either way couldn't it?
We will tee that one up when it comes.
first diver just making her way up to the 10 meter board there five dives they all go in different directions five different dives from the six available groups of dive from the platform so that's forwards and backwards inwards which is where you stand backwards and spin forwards towards the diving board
the reverse which is where you stand forwards and jump away spinning backwards towards the diving board and the twist which is where you rotate longitudinally as well and also the arm stand group so five dives out of those six groups so you'll see lots of different dives at different times but we can explain a little more as we go along when the final gets underway
What I can explain for you in terms of the dives in the first round, you will see nine out of the twelve divers go for a forward three and a half with difficulty of three point zero in the pike position.
The first five and nine out of twelve will do this particular dive, including the opening diver, Iulia Pirolopchuk of Ukraine.
Getting this contest underway.
The audience is filling up as we speak.
Very busy Olympic Park.
I'm sure most of the seats will be taken.
So first diver, the pike shape there, letting her down a little bit.
She needs to be tighter in a pike shape so the chest should be flat on the legs.
She chooses not to hold around the back of the thighs and link hand to elbow, which is what a lot of the divers do.
It's a peculiar technique.
She does a good job though.
Well, that's the opening gambit from her.
70.50 for Prodopchuk of Ukraine.
As I mentioned, you'll see that dive performed pretty much by all of the divers in the first round.
All I will say about this lady until she gets going is Paolo Espinoza Sanchez of Mexico.
Well, that's much better than the prelims, much better than the semi-final.
Has Paola finally woken up?
Whatever she's had to do this afternoon, she needs to refocus.
It all looks good so far, fantastic aerial work as always, just tipping over a vertical, but that should sneak a few seven and a halfs and eights.
It looks like a better opening dive.
from the Mexican.
Which way is it going to go for this evening?
I was feeling personally responsible for underperforming both in the prelims and the semis.
So I'm just keeping my distance and keeping my counsel on what she does here.
70.50.
So she matches Pragopchuk with the same dive.
And here comes Naomi Batki of Italy.
Likewise.
Oh, that's the best one so far.
That's the best one out of the three.
We can definitely compare like for like.
So approaching the end of the diving board with speed.
You need to turn that forward momentum into upward momentum, driving those hips up and over, squeezing into that pike shape.
That's a really good pike shape.
There was no daylight in between the chest and the thighs.
Look at that beautiful dive from the Italian.
The other two dives got 70.50.
Batki is looking for a bigger score than that.
Same tariff.
Different score though.
76.50.
Remember the marks with the lines through them do not count.
8.5s across the board do.
Multiplied by the degree of difficulty.
That's how you arrive at her starting figure.
Her first round score of 76.50.
Here's Hu.
Well, there is something wrong with this young lady.
Now, the Chinese keep their cards close to their chest, so no one knows whether she's injured, ill, but there's definitely something amiss.
She is world silver medalist from last year.
Yes, she's only 16 years old, but she was silver medalist behind the Olympic champion last year, and she is all over the shop again.
So this means the medals are wide open.
If Yudan continues to dive like this, she will be miles off the pace.
This is interesting.
Yeah, she's only had really one dive of caliber, of quality this morning, and likewise last night.
And the coach is giving her...
Let's stay here.
A few well-chosen words by the looks of things.
As we move on to Rosaline Fillon, our candidate.
Same dive once again, ranked 8th in the semi-final.
Let's see if she can match the Batki dive.
She looked a little tired this morning and I'm not surprised these girls finished late last night in the preliminaries and had to get up early this morning to dive in the semi-finals.
Roslyn looked a little bit off her game and this looks a better effort for her.
It's only going to get sevens throwing up a little bit too much splash.
squeezing into the pike shape seems to be moving ahead to the side there for some reason bit peculiar but she ended up on her head which is where she wanted to be now a reminder of course the judges do not see the replay that you see we see several times from different angles they only get one look at it in real time so and there's little nuances that early on might point out
are probably not apparent and not obvious to the judges in their position down below.
63 for Filion, different dive from Christian Stirr, 2.8 inwards, two and a half somersault, so low tariff needs to be good.
Well that's the best one she's done out of the three.
So prelims it was awful.
The semi-final she stepped up and she's starting with the weakest dive.
2.8 degree of difficulty.
Now we've seen some girls hit their feet on this.
Stoya not too far away from the platform.
It's very difficult to jump far enough away and still complete the rotations.
She's probably going to get sevens on that but because of the low degree of difficulty struggled to get over 60 points.
Yeah, just struggling past the sixty barrier.
Sixty point two zero for Kristen Stewart who has just rushed back to turn the gas off.
Now to Yulia Kolton over and there is only one arm stand in the first round so my heart can beat a regular pace for a change.
Crowd who haven't seen this before, oohing and ahhing already on the arm stand forward double somersault, one twist.
Well, she started beautifully in the semi-final with this dive.
That one there, she's just overcooked it.
Giving it a little bit too much on the start meant that it was very difficult to control with that much rotation.
So bending at the arms, flicking off very much like a gymnastics vault, wrapping into the twist.
There we are, just over rotating as she goes in there.
Maybe seven and a halfs on that.
It's a real shame because
It's very confident to open with the armstands.
That takes some nerves, doesn't it?
Oh, control of your nerves, I should say.
Takes some nerve.
Well, 72.85 is what she has accrued from that.
Everybody else, of course, doing an armstand.
Most of them a little later on.
Pretty much all in the third round.
So she opens her program with an armstand, which currently puts her in second place behind the Italian bat key.
Now, there's the Malaysian.
Back we go to the forward three and a half again with Pike.
Oh, is she feeling the pressure?
She's been performing very well and she's got herself in the business end of the field through her performance in the semi-final.
Only 19 years old.
I really like her diving.
Superb flexibility.
Look at that.
Her nose is almost touching her ankles.
Her flexibility is that good.
However, she's let the dive go over, which means it's your struggle to get more than sixes.
Six and a half on that.
And she's off the pace.
Yeah, not the start that she had in either the prelims or the semis.
So a little bit of reparation work already to be done for Angela Pang of Malaysia.
On to the two Australians now.
Again, a four, three and a half for the slightly older of the two Aussies, Melissa Wu.
Oh, very smooth, beautiful entry.
What the judges are looking for is a vertical entry with absolutely no splash.
And Melissa Wu was bang on the money with that one.
Her opening dive, you've seen this before.
Lots of the girls opening with this one.
Seems to be a very popular choice.
It's 3.0.
She's going to get 8.5 for sure on that one.
It's just what the judges are looking for.
She's up the game.
She's moved the bar upwards.
Wow, 78.
And disappeared without a trace into the water.
That's what you want to see.
And that's what she wanted to do.
And she has achieved that with great alacrity.
Well done, Melissa Wu.
Good start for her.
78 puts her into a lead.
Coaches still not happy.
They never are.
From the 20-year-old Australian to the 16-year-old Australian, Brittany Broban, 2.7, low degree of difficulty to start off with.
It's a reverse 2.5 somersaults with tuck.
oh she's played just a little bit safe what a shame because this was an absolute core cut in the semi-finals it had nines written all over it this one all the way until the water and she just keeps her chin in a little bit she didn't look back enough in order to get it round to the vertical position there we are she just needed to pull back a little bit she's gonna get seven and a half but what a shame because
Wow, she would have needed nines.
It's a low degree of difficulty.
This young lady's got some work to do.
She's going to live up to the, well, my prediction of a medal for her.
Come on.
Yeah, I put the mouth on poor Mexican.
Likewise for you with the Australian, it would seem, because that's not the best dive by quite some way that Broban has done over the last two days.
On to the second of the Canadians.
Here's Megan Benfito again, a forward three and a half.
Ooh, here we go.
I wondered when we would see the first mistake.
Archer there showing with his body language that that was very poor.
Wow, I didn't expect to see a mistake of that magnitude from this young lady, especially she's been one of the more consistent competitors through the prelims and the semi, which was a, wow.
it's all over the shop actually wow what a shame lots of splash over onto her back low marks incoming now what a shame especially as it looks like even early stages of silver and bronze might be up for grabs today and five point fives just will not cut it if you're looking to get into second or third place first place surely is secured before we even start by a chen
That's how you should do it.
That's definitely worth eight and a halfs and nines Superb technically very very good pops up into that pike shape No daylight in between the chest and the air at chest and the thighs drills the entry Superb and away she goes
Well, the crowd are getting excited.
Now, why are they getting excited?
Well, because there's a 10 on the scoreboard.
Sadly, as in previous competition, it doesn't count.
Was it worth a 10?
But the 9.5s most certainly do.
And 85.50, she's already proving.
She's in a class of her own, because look at the gap after round one.
She's already got a gap of seven points over Melissa Wu in second, Naomi Bakke in third, Yulia Koltanova in fourth.
Paolo Espinoza-Sanchez, much better start from her this time round.
Those are the ones in early stages pushing for the medals.
Rosalind Filion not too far away, but Megan Benfito at the bottom of the pile, along with Wu Yudan.
11th place for the Chinese.
Now, the coach made it very clear exactly what she thought of that dive.
She's gone away with a flea in her ear.
Only for round number two, which starts now.
second round of the women's 10 meter platform final already developing into a very interesting contest not so much for the main place but for the silver and the bronze and there are plenty in competition for that including Julia Prokopchuk up to 3.2 on the degree of difficulty for her in with three and a half somersaults equal fifth after first round oh she sneaks that one in just beautifully
Wow.
An okay start, backed up with one of her highest degrees of difficulty, an inward three and a half.
That's a safe distance from the diving board.
Some of the girls have been coming in a little bit too close for comfort.
I think that's going to just get over 70 points.
She's certainly laid a marker down.
Let's see what happens after.
This is
Seven point fives for seventy-two complete.
I'm not sure if sneaking in is in the Leon Taylor drinking game, but it should be because we'll be getting rather Brahms in this by the end of the evening.
Now on to Paula Espinosa-Sanchez of Mexico.
Back three and a half somersaults with Tuck.
Three point three the degree of difficulty for the Mexican.
Oh, she's more on her game, but still, you know, I think that says it all.
That's actually the Italian coach.
She's kind of going, well, it's OK, but we expect to see more from this accomplished diver.
She's got medals from everywhere.
Already Olympic medalist here, silver medal in the 10 meter synchro.
And that is good.
But I was expecting to see nines at her very best and all get seven, seven point fives going over a vertical as she goes in.
the divers holding there.
You can see the heavy the the wrist tapes to help with the impact.
Just see the feet coming towards us there and there's the wave.
Catch a wave and she did and she didn't really want to produce that but seventy-four point two five is good enough to put her into first place marginally at this stage.
Good start from Naomi Bakke.
She's gone from a three point zero down to a two point nine in round two.
He comes
That's probably her weakest dive in the program.
Leaning away from the diving board a little bit too far there, which means it's very difficult to control the dive.
And therefore, when you're looking for that precise entry, vertical entry, you just sometimes get some drift, which is what happened there.
Over as she goes in, throwing up a little bit of splash.
Just see the body tension required to hold yourself when you're hurtling towards the water.
incredible impact speeds.
She holds on to it there.
See what the judges think.
That's what they think.
Seven point fives across the board in terms of the marks that count.
Sixty-five point two five.
Remember, it is a degree of difficulty.
After those marks have been added up and the multiplied gives you sixty-five point two five.
Now, who you Dan?
There's a mystery regarding her at the moment.
Why is she diving so
Oh, good night.
You cannot make glaring errors like that and expect to feature on the podium.
Now it's wide open for the rest of the ladies.
Wow, this is really interesting.
She's a little tight to the platform there.
While aerial work is good, she just doesn't seem to know where she is.
I wonder if it'll come out after the contest if there is anything wrong with her from an illness point of view or an injury because she is way off her game.
Well, it looks like the coach doesn't want to talk to her.
She's running a bit of consolation there and the coach just kind of walked to one side and says, no, you get on with it.
And forty three point two zero.
How do you know what she said?
Do you speak Cantonese?
No, I'm just looking at her body language.
That's my interpretation.
Thank you, Leon.
Rosalind Filion now back with three and a half somersaults.
Tuck three point three.
Oh, there you go.
She saved the best until the final.
This young lady was way off the pace in the prelims and in the semifinal, hence her early start position in this final.
This is the dive that was giving her difficulty.
She's woken up and she saved her best back three and a half until now.
This is big because you can't see where you're going.
You're spinning backwards.
You can only see where you've been.
You have to point your feet up, which she does well.
Spot on.
Good work.
Yeah.
Nod to the coach and she can go into the plunge ball.
Very happy that she's picked up seventy five point nine zero and that lifts her up to fourth place.
Not that far behind the main movers and shakers.
of Germany.
Moved up from the ranks of the upper twos to the early threes.
Six, six, three point two.
I think I want to try six point two.
Oh, she's renowned for her very clean entries.
What you're looking for is a splashless entry.
And that's what Stewart is famed for.
Her takeoffs are very average indeed.
So she's quite weak, not as dynamic or strong as some of the other girls, but she can certainly get her dives in.
with hardly a ripple of splash.
And that will probably get seven and a halfs, maybe an eight.
Here come the judges' marks.
And yeah, they're going with you on that.
They're going with the eights and giving her a total accumulative score of 76.80.
And again, she's bunching up in quite a large pack of seven marks surrounding five divers at this stage.
That's how tight this competition is.
Hewlett-Colton over, fourth after round one.
Oh, just going a little bit loose in the lower back as she went in.
Her takeoff is a little bit weak, which means the dive is always going to finish very, very low to the water, which means that you need to do a, well, do a pretty good job of getting out of it very, very quickly and trying to hide that from the judges.
Just see there, just turning into a bit of a banana woman as she goes in.
See on the super slow motion arching through the lower back.
Yeah, just needed a little bit more speed to that rotation in order to give herself a fraction more time.
It's okay, but needed to be better.
Yeah, okay.
Probably won't quite make it done in the final for her.
She needs a bit better than that.
Needs more consistency than that.
And 61.05 for Coltenova means that she's back in sixth place.
Pandela Pang of Malaysia, 2.9, back two and a half somersaults.
Oh, it's an absolute corker.
Shaky first round dive, there we go.
There are teammates shouting and screaming and so would I be.
beautiful takeoff such so strong fantastic look how she glides out with her feet pointing down at the water and absolutely buries the entry it's only 2.9 but when you score nines on it like she will do here keeps you in the mix good work yeah what a shame she started with a 58.5 or she'd be right up there as it is she's not too far adrift she's made up some ground with that
78.30 and she is up to sixth but uh I'll tell you six up to one separated by eight points at the moment early stage of course only round two into another of those um stands there are three point two variety and a three point three variety and there will be a three point one as well a little later on but the most uh popular choice of the three point two which this is um stand back double somersault one and a half twist for Wu
It's important that you show a steady arm balance to the judges before you go.
And I think Melissa managed that.
And then this is where the hard work starts.
Just flick the legs, lift up the shoulders into the twist, and then finish that dive off.
That's consistent.
Sevens on this, seven and a halfs maybe to go with her first round dive, which is a good score.
78, I think, first round.
Seventy-two this round.
It's good.
Yeah, into the lead she goes.
It's a lead of about six points.
She is setting the mark for everybody else to follow including her Australian teammate.
That's Brittany Broban.
Sixteen years of age.
In with three and a half somersaults.
Three point two in the tuck position for Brittany Broban.
It's tremendous that should get nines and nine point fives Wow, there you go.
She knows it's such a good feeling when you get a dive like this that drills into the water It's okay It's a safe distance and this feeling when you bury a dive like that.
It's almost like you're being teleported somewhere else It's extraordinary noise in the ears a buzz through the body into the water
big score 83 yeah very big score indeed and again just a shame that her first die was not that accurate and not executed to the full and to the max because she would be very much at the top as it is she's third with that 83.20 now megan benfito
has some ground to make up already it's not irretrievable 3.3 back three and a half again tuck position Megan finding herself in the unaccustomed position 12th after round one oh that's going to help that certainly is going to help such a shame when you blow your opening dive and you leave yourself with so much to do
But she's obviously left that dive where it is.
There's nothing else you can do but focus on the next one.
And that is a corker to come back with.
Wow.
We're finally seeing some high quality dives from the ladies.
Well, we are.
But from her point of view, she'll look up at the scoreboard in a moment and see the classification after round two.
And she will know that she hasn't actually made up a lot of ground at all in terms of places.
At the moment, she's gone from 12th to 10th.
and uh you imagine this lady will have number one beside her name and she has done all the way through the preliminaries and semi-finals just oozing confidence and hardly putting a foot wrong so far in with three and a half some assaults for the runaway number one Chinese at the moment performed in the tuck position here comes Chen Ruolin world and Olympic champion
Oh, it's fabulous.
Not worth a ten, maybe nines on that.
The only thing incorrect or the only thing wrong with that dive was there was a little bit of splash thrown up.
Technically perfect.
Jumps up over the diving board, squeezing into a perfect tuck shape.
Kicks out through a pike position.
Very, very well executed.
It'll get over 80 points.
Just showing her class here.
Look at the ankle snap there.
Droplets of water.
Tape on the lower back to support an injury she has, but wow.
She does not look as though she's going to get caught.
Follows up an 85.5 with an 84.8 and already a massive chasm between one and the rest.
Already a lead of 20 points.
Really?
Yes.
20 points between the Chinese and the rest.
And here comes the standings after round two.
170 already accrued for Chen Ruolin.
Then Melissa Wu and Paolo Espinosa-Sanchez in third.
Brittany Brobin not far away or indeed Ilya Rodopchuk.
And we're starting to cast a few adrift at the bottom and look who is at the bottom.
Who is at the bottom?
Very interesting first two rounds.
Just to confirm how the judging works, there are seven judges.
Each of the judges mark out of ten.
The two highest and two lowest marks are discounted to leave the three remaining marks.
Those are the three without the lines through.
Those three marks are then added together, multiplied by the degree of difficulty to give the total for that particular dive.
Round three, first diver Iulia Pugopchuk, only 2.9, back two and a half somersaults with Pike.
it's good she is having a consistent performance 2.9 degree of difficulty some of the girls going for the backward three and a half this young lady and for the slightly easier backward two and a half pikes and it's very good she just lets her legs drop there and arches into a lower back doesn't seem to affect the end she struggled to get more than seven and a half so as it just drifts over a vertical
Look at the tension on the audience faces when the divers are going through the air.
Friends, family, and acquaintances through agony, all of them.
And 65.25 for Pregopchuk.
And she becomes the first diver to go through the 200 barrier.
Now, Balot Espinosa-Sanchez reversed three and a half somersaults with Tuck.
She's worked her way up to number three after round number two.
oh it's good she's just a little bit over throwing the splash up towards the diving board she's the only female performing this dive the men all do this dive you need to be incredibly strong incredibly dynamic to perform the reverse three and a half and she does it almost effortlessly but just overcooks it over a vertical well i don't know sixes maybe but
I'm impressed with the dive that it's so difficult but not so impressed with the execution.
Maybe she's thinking that wasn't really part of the plan and certainly wasn't really a dive perhaps I should have included in my program but it's a program she will have done time and time again.
Feels comfortable enough with it but not feel that comfortable with a score of sixty one point zero five which temporarily at least puts her into second place now.
Naomi
Back two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists, formed in the pike position.
Yep, straight up and down, marginally short as she went into the water.
It's quite complex, lots of the girls will be finishing on this dive.
3.2 degree of difficulty, so the potential is that you can score very well on it indeed.
Over 70 points would be a good score.
Over 80 points should be even better.
I think this would get early seventies.
It does.
Seventy-two for Naomi Baki.
Seven point fives will count.
The other scores do not.
Seventy-two is the total score for the Hungarian born Italian.
Now, who you Dan?
place after round two.
Obviously out of sorts for reasons that we don't really know.
Onward back double somersaults and this has got three point two attached to it.
Well, that's more like it.
She was straight up and down.
Vertical entry.
throwing up a little bit of splash.
She doesn't have any tape on her, nothing on the wrist, nothing on the ankles.
Lots of the divers adding support to some of the joints with tape.
Who you done?
That's much more like it, but she's left herself way too much to do.
That's a good shot, isn't it?
Close up on the face, popping up into that twist.
Technically very, very good indeed.
A little bit of splash being thrown up.
Other than that, it's a good dive.
One of the few we've seen from this young lady.
Yeah, she left it, as Leon was saying, way too late, though.
Mathematically, everybody else would have to go sideways and not complete their dives for her to be in with a chance.
It's just too much of a hill to climb now for her.
Roslyn Filion.
In seventh, after round two.
Inward three and a half somersaults with tuck.
Seen it before.
Here it is again, worth 3.2 in terms of degree of difficulty.
Oh, a little bit loose as she went in, not quite holding the tension.
The coach is obviously clapping anyway.
Just, there we go, arching in the lower back, not quite holding the tension.
Takeoff is good, a little bit low on the water, so it needed to be sharp out there.
You can see just a little bit of, you know, wavering in the body tension, throwing up that splash.
Probably get sevens.
Not quite as good as her previous dive, which got 76.
Yeah, it doesn't match the seventy five point nine zero.
She got in round two sixty seven point two zero and uh just waiting again for anybody other than to take this competition by the scruff of the neck and say I want a medal because nobody yet from her has really shown their full range and their top competitive instincts.
Now the arm stand back double somersault, one and a half twists, fresh dirt.
Overcooked it, too much on the start.
So it's very important that you pop up into this dive.
If you lean too far, you get too much whip and that causes increased rotation, which is exactly what Storia does here.
And she just can't stop it and over she goes.
So, that will move her slightly down the field.
It's a little bit further away from standing on the podium.
Yeah.
Well, nothing you can do about it now.
Four divers have gone over two hundred.
She has not as yet.
And you gotta be up there to be in the medal contention and she is fifth currently.
There are quite a few divers still to go including Julia Carlton over three point zero.
degree of difficulty four three and a half oh I really like that the aerial work is superb she spins she's got a really fast rotation giving her plenty of time to line up she does let the dive go over a vertical only marginally so this could get eights slightly poor second round dive has left her a little bit off the pace only tenth after round two she will move up after that good third round effort
There we go.
I have a feeling that my calculator might be uh glowing steam out by the end of this evening and it's going to be an awful lot of uh numbers to crunch at the end of this competition because they are so so tight for the minor medals.
If we ignore the uh Victor and gold medalist elect again, everybody else is starting to bunch up in that two to eight position.
3.2 degree of difficulty on this arm stand back double somersault one and a half twists
Oh she's done exactly the same as Kristin she has gone after the dive a little bit too aggressively and therefore she's gone yeah she knows you can tell by body language here we go just a little bit too aggressive and then when she re-pikes can't stop it from going over you can see the splash moving away from the diving board six and a halfs sevens at best
Angelina moving further away from the podium, dive after dive.
Starting with a 58, comes in with a 64 this time on a 3.2 dive.
She's been looking for up at 70s, so probably a tariff of minus 15 on that.
That means that she's not really pushing, although she's not that far adrift because everybody else is hitting very similar figures to her right now.
Melissa Wu back three and a half somersault with tuck.
Is this the dive that might cause us some problems?
She's been pretty impeccable today.
3.3 degree of difficulty, biggest one that she does.
Oh you caught it Bob I was doing my hand signal with a shaking hand which means this is the bogey dive which way is it going to go and the answer to that is short.
Short of vertical on the entry just running out of room she drifts back a little bit too far kicks out a fraction too early lands short of vertical five and a halfs and sixes and that puts the cat amongst the pigeons and everyone is bunched up
Apart from Shenu Lin, everyone's bunched up, so no one wants their silver or bronze, looks like.
Now, does Brittany Brobin want to break out of the pack and show her metal, 16 years of age, showing that she's a very mature 16-year-old.
Hasn't got phased by anything here.
This will be a real test for her, though.
Again, it's the 3.2 arm stand.
I think we'll have a 3.3 coming later, but it's the 3.2 version of it.
Arm stand back, somersaults, somersaults?
That's the time of the season of course.
Back and double somersaults.
One and a half twists.
Oh yes, oh yes!
Wow, that is bang on the money.
It doesn't get better than that.
That entry is just, wow, dare I say, as near perfect as it needs to be.
If anything, she could do with being a little bit tidier in the air, but that is a splashless entry.
Really, really good.
Judges will probably penalise because she was losing her feet and legs a little bit in the air.
They have, but look at that, 8.5s and 9s, 83.
Hello, Australia.
8.5 and nine.
It's your catchphrase there, sorry.
But a very good dive for the second Australian who's becoming very much the first Australian here as Brobin goes into a fourteen point lead.
Obviously won't hang around for too long.
You see Canadian will be followed very shortly by the Chinese, but here comes Ben Fito's in with three and a half.
She's eleventh after round two.
So these dives now have to be absolutely impeccable if she stands any chance of making a challenge.
No, she's got it on her head.
She is the right way up.
Just in shot there, that's her shammy.
The divers use that to dry off the legs so they can grip onto the shins here as Megan's demonstrating.
If your hands are wet and shins are wet, you can slip out and that isn't very good at all.
Also for drying themselves off and keeping warm.
This is good, but she's left herself way too much to do.
What an absolute shame.
Yeah, not her day.
Seventy-two is an okay mark but it's not good enough what she needs at this stage.
Now the crowd appreciating talent.
There's a lot of Chinese supporters in the crowd but I think everybody just knows how good this young lady is.
Olympic and world champion.
Nineteen years of age now.
arm stand back double somersault again 3.2 already with a 20 point lead and adding to that lead dive after dive so consistent plenty of Chinese support here and we are seeing a master at work here she is one and a half twist double somersault drilling the entry just a little bit too much splash for more than a nine but
Three point two, nines across the board.
Big score, increased lead.
Yeah, 29 points now, 20 up to 29 and minute details.
Maybe she's doing wrong, but for the majority of the time, for most of the dives, it isn't a great deal.
You can fault it by
256, 29 point lead for Chen Ruolin.
Brittany Brobin into second, 14 point lead for her, for third, over Bakke, and then they're keying up behind Prokopchuk, Filion and Wu, all on that page.
Maybe over 200, probably still just about there.
Colton over, Sanchez, Benfito and Pang, and Hu Yudan.
You're downed if you do, you're downed if you don't.
So fourth to eleventh, there is what?
Seven or eight points.
Bunched up.
Nice to see Brobin in second place.
My tip.
Shame I didn't have a bet.
Round four.
Opening diver.
Yulia Prokopchuk.
And here comes the arm back triple somersault.
Talking about the 3.2s, first time we get to see the 3.3 in this competition.
So the tariff a bit higher, the risk a bit higher too.
Oh, she's smoked it, as some of the divers say.
When you get into the water without any splash, there's many different terminologies used.
I've just picked one out of the archives there and she's smoked it.
Wow, 3.3, high risk, high degree of difficulty.
Armstand back, triple somersault in the tuck position.
Beautiful fourth round dive from the Ukrainian.
Keeping himself in contention.
Good distance from the board.
Good marks across the board.
Eight, eight and eight.
Three point three degree of difficulty.
When you add it all up comes to seventy nine point two zero and she has put herself in a good position for a medal and currently in first place.
Paolo Espinosa Sanchez of Mexico in with three and a half with Tuck
Oh, that's her best dive so far.
She just has this tendency to go in with a slight back arch, which gives the impression she's much further over a vertical than she actually is.
That's her best dive so far.
You can't fault this lady's takeoffs.
They are spot on.
The entry into the water, letting her down yet again.
It's going to be her high-scoring dive and get eight 8.5s.
I don't know whether well maybe she can bring herself back in contention.
One dive to go.
80 points is good.
80 points is very good but is it enough not to take the lead?
It's not because Prokopchuk has got that by just over a mark and that's how tight this competition really is.
Naomi Bakke is currently in third place in with three and a half for her.
80 or 85, and she goes flying back up the standings again.
All feeling the pressure, third after the third round.
Maybe surprised her to see herself so far up the field.
And this is one of her most difficult dives.
Safe distance from the diving board, just hanging onto her tuck shape a little bit too long, just a fraction.
Over rotating, you'll only get, oh, I don't think it will get 70.
So, shuffling the pack once again.
Yeah, it's almost kind of right.
Well, you have a go now.
I'm quite happy to sit back and watch you do something good or bad or indifferent.
Sixty-eight point eight zero for backkeep.
And she goes, well, she's at third now but she won't be staying there for very long.
Sorry for her.
She's just so far off her game today.
Back three and a half with Tuck.
This young 16-year-old silver medalist, there we are, the coach is a big beam in smile, she knows what she can do.
This girl dives all day, every day at such a standard and this is a standard that I am accustomed to commentating on from this...
superb talent from China, but she has messed up her first two dives so considerably that even though this is going to score nearly 90 points, I would imagine, she will still only be creeping up the field at best.
Wow, look at that, 89.
highest mark of the competition with those nines multiplied by three point three and uh she has moved up a few places but she is still twenty-three points behind and twenty-two behind Sanchez and that's going to be a lot of ground to make up three point three crowd not really helping in terms of getting in an upright position there arm stand back triple
Oh, it's good.
She couldn't quite hold the splash down.
Really strong takeoff.
Her heels almost touch the back of her legs as she bends.
In fact, they do.
Lower back, in fact.
Flicks in, holding a little bit high on her knees there.
Just letting the dive go marginally over.
So it's 3.3.
So get a good score.
It'll get over 70 points.
If she was more upright, she would have been even more pleased with that.
Throwing up too much splash.
72.60 for the time being, she moves up into fourth behind Pragopchuk, Sanchez and Bakke.
But only eight points behind the current leader.
So that's makeable.
Christian Sturr of Germany finds herself at the wrong end of the table.
11th.
And this is a low tariff dive, which may not help her in her reparation.
Back two and a half.
Oh, what a dive!
That's exactly what she did in the semi-finals, very experienced.
And this is exactly how you finish off a dive.
A little bit low, height-wise.
That's why she goes for the slightly easier backward moving once she gets in the water there with hardly a ripple of splash.
A little bit arched through the lower back here as she pulls it round.
But you can't fault that entry.
Hiding behind there, there she comes, and here come the mark, 73.95.
I can tell you that Yulia Koltanova of Russia up next, 8.5s across the board, and she will go into the lead, which obviously is second place in terms of this competition with the number one Chinese dominating, but she can go right up to second overall if she gets this 3.2 right.
Oh, and she does.
She gets it bang on the money.
Well predicted, Bob.
I was watching this in training.
It was a little bit here and there.
We might even crack a smile at the end of the competition, but at the moment she has her game face on.
She's a bit too close to the diving board though.
Sorry for the change in tonality.
I've seen too many divers, a little bit too close.
Anyway, she's safely by the diving board, drills the entry and the judges all award highly for that.
I'm sure they do.
Not often heard on the worldwide television, but Leon Taylor's Tarzan impression is coming along quite nicely, I think.
Just a little whimper.
Don't worry about me.
Yeah, that's how you're known by us.
Seventy-eight point four zero for Colton Over, who goes into third place, but is oh so tight at the top.
Pandela Pang of Malaysia in with three and a half, three point two.
Yeah, well that's what this young lady can do.
I had her down as a medal chance and she's faltered on a few of the rounds, left herself too much to do.
But that is bang on the money.
This inward three and a half superb height.
He's a little bit close to the diving board as well.
those of you that are tweeting saying how come the divers are so close well i agree with you they are a little bit too close but if you move too far away from the diving board you'll never make this amount of rotation so it's a fine line between being close enough to make it and far enough away for safety she's back in the mix 81.6 she's only four points behind in effect second place but here come the two australians who have been impressive and are looking to get
Silver and bronze to kind of turn around the Australians week in the Aquatic Centre in with three and a half somersaults with tuck for Melissa Wu.
Oh, she's got it right on her hands, right on her head, as we say, in diving, which is actually a good thing, so upright.
But just throwing up a little bit of splash, swallowed a bit of water there as she went in, looks like.
Aerial work is great, tuck shape is superb, all bang on the money.
Just look at that, shooting up the water.
So maybe she'll get some eights.
If she was clean, as in no splash, she would have got 8.5s and nines.
Just a shame.
Did she not quite lock out on the finish, maybe?
The water just, ba-boom.
What marks she got for that?
How much did it help her?
How much did it hinder her?
75.2048 and a 7.5 and Melissa Wu actually slips a couple of places and is back in sixth.
Now can her Australian colleague react more favorably, more positively with a back three and a half.
3.3 for Broban currently in second place.
Sixes will keep her there.
Oh, I think it's going to get sixes.
Oh, she will look back on that.
and think, uh-oh, I think that's the dive that could have potentially cost me a certain Olympic medal.
Still to play for.
If she does get sixes, which I think she will, that's going to put her very much bunched up in this fight for the silver and bronze.
What a shame.
Robin could have capitalized there.
If she'd have nailed that, she would have pretty much guaranteed herself a medal.
Now she's going to have to fight like crazy in the last round.
5.56 and six will count times the degree of difficulty 57.75.
You will not believe the scoreboard at the end of this round.
Just wait and see.
It is absolutely astonishing how tight it is.
Megan Benfito, one and only, of course.
Arm stand, only done once in the competition, and this is the big one, three point three.
Now, if she does get this right, she then jumps back into that pack.
She needs to be at the top of the game.
Eight point fives will put her into first place.
and that certainly won't get 8.5s it's a shame because the aerial work and the takeoff was good she was just out a little bit early of the spin she's throwing the water away there frustrated annoyed she knows that her olympic dreams of an individual medal are slipping away just as she slips short into the water there
She might get some sevens but she would have needed eight and a halfs and nines to bring her back into that sandwich that is around the second to seventh.
I would call it a smorgasbord actually, more than a sandwich.
It is ridiculous how tight it is.
With the exception, of course, of one diver who is in a different competition in a league of her own and already with almost a 30-point lead after three rounds.
Almost up to 260 points already.
Chen Ruolin back three and a half.
Yeah, it's very good.
It's marginally short vertical.
It's a splash as entry as she goes in.
She really is a cut above everyone else in this field.
It's a one-horse race out here today and this is the horse we're looking at here as she drills into the water.
It's probably not going to get in the 80s but this will be the first dive of hers that doesn't.
It won't be far away but just a little marginally short.
Here are the marks.
79.20, her lowest mark of the evening, but in the 80s all the way through, slips into the 70s, but marginally.
But her lead is 49 points.
Now look at this.
Look at this.
286, 285, 284, 284, 282.
Holy moly.
There is nothing to pick between second to sixth.
Let's see where seventh is.
Where's seventh?
Oh, she's on 282.
282 as well.
281.
278.
So that is second to ninth.
All in contention.
Wow, it doesn't get any closer than that.
Thank you, girls, because you have just...
brought this competition alive.
A shoddy prelim, a shoddy semi, and a super tight last round into the final.
Where will the medals go?
One to that young lady.
Yeah, nobody can afford a slip up here.
Two to nine, separated by virtually nothing at all.
So everybody in the first half of the groupings up for a medal,
Oh, she doesn't want a medal.
She has decided with her last dive that she does not want a medal.
She's feeling the pressure.
Maybe she looked at the scoreboard, maybe she didn't.
We will not know.
Aerial work is good.
You'll see a lot of the girls do this one to finish.
One and a half twist.
Two and a half somersaults way over into the water.
Now, after some fabulous diving, she's gone and let it all go on this final dive.
She'll play that over and over in her head.
Wow, the door is just swung open.
Look, the teammates say it all.
Head in the hand stuff.
Ouch.
Here's a mark.
Oh, no.
57.60.
Dear, dear, dear.
She was right on top of her game in dive number four, and right off her game in dive number five.
So that could well be Bogapchuk gone in terms of medal.
Now, this lady was the bronze medal winner last year at the World.
So she knows how to do it.
At the moment, she is in third place.
3.2 to finish off the program.
It's back two and a half somersaults.
One and a half twist has been done by most of the divers in the final round, round five.
Oh, well, it's okay.
Now, it needed to be better than that to guarantee a medal.
It could end up being good enough, but, well, she really is off her game.
Exactly the same dive as we saw from
The Ukrainian and the Mexican there not managing to capitalize.
The door was open.
I think she's going to get above.
She'll be in the lead currently, only second diver in.
Not good enough for a medal, I don't think, though.
Wait and see.
70.40 is the mark.
I see what everybody else does yet, of course, but 7.5 and a seven.
She would have hoped for a great deal better than that.
That's the end of her program.
It's a hug from the coach.
And now just has to sit and wait and see if that's good enough.
It may not be.
She is in number one position right now.
All the main protagonists around her are still to go, including
This rather surprise potential medalist in Naomi Badke from Italy.
Reverse two and a half, slightly different to everybody else in this final round.
It's only 2.7 though, so it's got to be absolutely faultless.
Oh, it's very good.
It is very good.
But 2.7, she's finished on one of her lowest degree of difficulty.
I think the game of tactics not very well played.
It's obviously her favorite dive.
That's why she finishes on it.
But she can't match the 3.2s.
Wow, but it's a good effort.
8.5s, I don't think that will be good enough to get above Espinoza.
entry into the water.
Wow, the final round, the scoreboard just kind of grinds to a halt, doesn't it?
Let's see.
Still waiting.
Here they come.
And it isn't good enough to overtake the Mexican into second place.
And sadly, from her point of view, I think the look on her face will indicate exactly what she's thinking at 67.50 and 350.05.
means the best you can realistically do now is a bronze and hope that everybody else falters and the rest of the program not likely to happen.
Oh, she did perfect tens.
She would get into a medal position, but I wish she'd been diving today.
Oh, wow.
So that's going to get a bag full of nines, maybe even a nine point five.
So who you down has decided to wake up and do two near on perfect dives in round four.
She scored the highest scoring dive of the competition at 89.
This is probably going to be the second highest scoring dive of the competition.
She's just shown two bursts of brilliance and because of the quality of the competition so far and the hit and miss nature, she's probably put herself back not too far away from the podium.
Be very interesting to see.
Wow, here come the marks.
Oh, three, four, nine.
Just behind Bakhti.
Yeah, she is.
And just behind Sanchez, which means, in effect, she will not be getting a medal today.
Because her compatriot, her fellow Chinese, Chen Ruolin, has got so much in order.
to uh thought she'd secure the gold already but uh she just has to complete the dive in any fashion and she'll be okay and Roslyn Filion again not going to be in the medals today back two and a half somersaults one and a half twists pike three point two to finish yeah just a little bit over a fraction over as she goes in she's had a tough day but she did get better and better
as we move from the prelims to the semis to the final.
This young lady obviously already Olympic bronze medallist with Megan who's coming up later on as you know.
Here she is.
Final dive in the competition.
Well, it's so tight.
You never really know, do you?
You don't know.
And she doesn't know her marks yet.
They're making her wait a little bit before they appear on three seventy point four zero.
Another three four nine.
Yeah, we have uh two divers who and filling on on three four nine.
We have
That's how tight it is for the medals but Sanchez has a six-point advantage.
She currently is in what in effect is the silver medal position for the Mexican.
There she is waiting and hoping and knowing that she's been diving better tonight than she did in the prelims and in the semifinal as well.
Kristen Sturr just going to finish off her program with the dive that many did in the first round.
It's that forward three and a half somersaults with Pike to finish for the German.
What a fit what a dive to finish on as well what a finish to the dive to Buried the entry hardly a ripple of splash Again this Well, it's so so close she was tenth wasn't she after the fourth round I think with a lower degree of difficulty even though it's been performed exceptionally well, it's that standing dive to finish on and
Well, it's probably going to be a bit too much to stand on the podium, or is it?
No.
78.
Trombone time.
8.5 and 9.
She's gone into second place.
3.51.
Knocking Batki out of her medal.
And the German, who we thought was gone for all money, may not quite be yet.
But there's still some divers more highly ranked in terms of the standings than she, including Yulia Koltonova.
And it's a 3.2, like many of the others, a back 2.5 somersaults, 1.5 twists, 2.84 her current score.
Leads in the 70s.
Wow, I think that is going to go into the 70s.
Julia responding to the pressure, knows it's so tight.
There's nothing she can do apart from concentrate on the dive at hand.
And she has done a very good job.
Marginally short, she's gone in, but she's clean, tidy, and she was in fifth place before.
So I think she's going to top it.
That is good enough.
Let's wait and see.
It's an agonizing wait.
Come on, scoreboard.
Where are you?
Not kicked in yet.
No.
Something like Didier Smith there.
Just stop it.
73.
Oh, she's gone into top place.
She's overtaken Espinosa Sanchez by 1.7 points.
Now, it's not going to be gold for her, but at the moment, Koltunova is looking at a silver medal
Espinosa Sanchez is looking at a bronze.
But there's still some more to come, including Pandela Pang.
Same dive.
Same kind of mark needed.
75 or thereabouts might just get it done for her.
Oh, it's a good effort just marginally over a vertical.
Well, they're going to shout and cheer as loud as they can because they know they're teammates know how tight it is.
Wow, what a climax.
Well, if Panda Leather was just a little bit more vertical, they see just tipping over.
It's a shame.
It's a three point two again.
All the girls using this dive to finish on.
Ooh, she made some mistakes earlier in the program otherwise she'd have been guaranteed a medal.
Look at this, look at this.
Wow, there you go, 3.59.
She's gone into the lead.
Golden over down to two.
Espinosa Sanchez will not get a medal today.
goodness gracious me.
What drama.
Seventy-six point eight zero for the nineteen-year-old from Malaysia.
So, so we do a calculation.
Not guaranteed a medal yet though.
Just not.
Yeah, Melissa Wu's in contention of course.
Yeah, she's eight though.
In contention.
Well, she's still, it's still tight.
If she nails this.
It's gotta be around eighty though.
Yeah.
On this three point two.
Back two and a half semisoles, one and a half twist.
She's looking at the
Oh it's probably not clean enough a little bit too much splash she is upright there you see the other contenders they've done their dives now they have to wait and see what the judges think.
Melissa Roo giving her all on this last dive a little bit too far away from the diving board but she does get in it's tidy a little bit too much splash where will she finish oh my goodness
That's my client.
Agent there.
Boyfriend there.
Mark's coming very soon.
She can't wait.
We can't wait.
Oh, 358 just behind the Malaysian.
Yeah, she's into second place currently.
She might pick up a bronze, but there again, she might be edged out of it by her teammate, Brittany Brobin, 16 years of age.
And she needs, well, not as much.
To go into the lead, she needs 76.
This was my bet for the medal.
76 is all she needs, I say all she needs.
Still got to be executed this dive pretty accurately.
3.2, back 2.5, somersaults 1.5, look for 76 or above to go into the lead.
Yes, that's good enough.
That will be silver for the 16-year-old Australian.
What an incredible contest.
Yes, that is good enough.
That is good enough.
Wow.
Outstanding performance.
Well, it's not often I look into my crystal ball and predict something so accurately, but I did say after the prelims and the semi that this young 16-year-old is on for a medal, and that is the silver right there.
Well done.
Well done, Brittany.
Big smile, big mark, she's praying.
Here it comes, oh yeah!
Oh yes, 81.60 for Brittany Brobin, Australian silver.
It says one beside her name, but there's a Chinese who is far, far away in terms of competition.
And she is not going to catch her.
But what she has just captured is a silver medal.
And it will be, the way things are looking, Australian silver and Malaysian bronze, and Andalena Pang.
What a competition.
And that means that Melissa Wu misses out by just over one point from a medal.
It could have been Australian 2-3.
Megan Benfitto to finish off with for Canada.
Back two and a half again.
One and a half twists.
Oh, she's finished so strongly and she'll be kicking herself.
because of the few dives where she's been under par she didn't quite leave herself in contention for this well this final flourish that we've been seeing here in the final round all the girls choosing to do this most of them the back two and a half one and a half twists all finishing on the 3.2 dive for dive for dive for dive direct comparison
Some divers choosing to dive from the left hand or the right hand side of the board or the middle, it's complete preference.
And here we go, that agonising weight now.
So that computer has a bit of a sense of humour, just wants everybody to hold on for a little longer.
And 10th place is where she will finish.
Certainly not where she wanted to finish and she's distraught by that, thought she could do better.
Was expected to do better, but just wasn't her day.
Now let's round off with something of real class, real finesse and real expertise.
Never troubled, never really stepping out of line, always impeccable today.
It's been a masterclass of 10 meter platform diving from Chen Ruilin.
Back three and a half to finish.
No, same dive, back two and a half, one and a half twist.
Absolutely phenomenal performance from prelim to semi to final, retaining her Olympic title that she won when she was only 15 years old in Beijing.
Here she is at 19 and she is stormed to another victory.
She was the only diver here really in this competition.
It was a one-horse race.
She left everyone from dive one.
and this finishing off in fine style indeed showing her class there was a real fight for the lesser medals and Shen Ru Lin goes into diving history retaining her olympic title what a dive from this young lady and what a set of dives 86 to finish 86.40 she wins the competition by
56 points, 56 points between first place and second place and that is quite astonishing and quite astonishing too for that 16 year old from Australia who really cannot believe it but it's true pinch yourself
because it is 366.50 and she's going to go to friends and family and hug and kiss and it'll be just such an emotional moment for her.
Who's she trying to pick out?
The Australians are over that side.
She doesn't know what to do.
She doesn't know where to go, who to hug, who to talk to.
16 years of age.
A great semi and a fantastic final for Broban of Australia.
And let's not overlook that lady, bronze medalist for Hank
Thought at one stage she might have blown it.
She had to do a lot of work at the end.
This is how I finished them.
422.30 for Chen.
Broban winning her silver by seven, but the bronze only secured by Panda Lopang by 1.1 mark.
And everybody else below that line will go, oh, if only I'd done that.
If only I'd done that.
Huyudan did well to move up to ninth.
Iulia Pregopchuk on the basis of her opening dive in the last round, falling right down to the bottom and the two Canadians in 10th and 11th.
Well, that was absolutely anybody's for the silver and bronze.
Wow.
How tight.
I've not seen a competition that tight with the remainder of the pack.
Shenmue Lin way out in front and everyone else.
Wow, in the mix.
I didn't think anyone wanted it at one stage but this young lady certainly did.
Brittany Probin, 16 years old.
Handelela, 19 and the Olympic champion Shenmue Lin, 19.
So it's won by
Girls under the age of 19, top three.
And what is great about this is she really didn't know what to do.
Where do I go?
Who do I talk to?
What's the protocol now?
Can I go and see my family?
Can I go and say hello to my friends?
Or is there a medal stand?
She really didn't know.
It's like her head was spinning as she took in the realization that she's an Olympic silver medalist.
Yeah, I know what that feeling's like.
You have to keep calm, composed, focused when you're performing under such expectation and pressure and when you actually do it, when you look at that scoreboard and your name is next to a medal position, it's like the damn burst and all those emotions just flood
come flooding through and you don't know which way is up or down or sideways.
Look at that great embrace with our coach and there we are Brittany with her coach such a journey the hours and hours of hard work and dedication pay off
Embraces all around.
Wow.
And then of course, the fourth, fifth and sixth and seventh will be an eighth and ninth and tenth and eleventh and twelfth in this competition.
And we'll be thinking, what if, what if I was just a bit better on one of my dives?
Maybe, just maybe it would have been my moment, my moment to stand on that podium.
But today,
Chen was way out in front, Broban as well.
I backed him.
Silver medalist and Pandalena Pang.
Fantastic in bronze.
Wu just outside.
Well agonising, fourth place.
Now if you are a diver or a swimmer who has to get up at a ridiculously early hour of the morning, we know you do,
four o'clock, five o'clock in the morning to go to training.
This young lady who's just won the silver medal gets up at four fifteen every morning for training.
She has to go well over an hour to go to Brisbane, to the Gold Coast to train and obviously over an hour back.
She's still at school trying to combine all that.
and just see the reward it has brought to her by just digging in there and going, do you know what?
Four fifteen in the morning.
I don't really want to be getting out of bed but this is what I want to achieve and she has achieved it.
She's not achieved it as a fluke.
You may think because some of the bigger names failed a bit today or were slightly off the game.
No, she she didn't win it by default.
She won it on her own efforts there.
Just fantastic.
I was um must admit I was
through the semi-final, but that final turned out to be a real corker.
And as we wait for the moment when the medals are handed out, we just get a chance to reflect on the thrills we've had here in the diving pool.
Obviously, the Olympic Games started on the 27th, the diving first contest on the 29th, and we've been here every single day apart from one.
And we haven't left.
And we haven't left, yeah.
I think I just stay here.
I stay here with my headphones on, waiting for more action.
And yeah, so that was a slow, slow burner, the women's platform.
But what a exciting climax.
I can't ask for more than that.
More drama on the last round there, Bob, with our calculators and our, you know, predictions and crystal balls and wow.
Top eight all over 350.
The bronze 366, the silver rather 366, the bronze 359.
and right down to Bakke who again looked like she might be in there but what did for her and we keep making this point she had a low tariff dive to finish right at the end now she'd had a 3.1 or 3.2 or actually had gone for a broker then we might be talking about the Italian as a bronze medalist possibly a silver medalist but she went for an easy option an easier option shall we say in the last round and ultimately when everybody else is doing 3.2s and you're doing a 2.9
There's a big differential there.
Yeah, that's why it's 2.7.
Actually the die she finished on she's giving away 0.5 She of course used her 3.2 the back two and a half one and a half twist, which you saw All the ladies do in the final round.
That is a game of tactics It probably didn't work out for Naomi back to there from Italy finishing in eighth when she was very much in there for a medal
What about the Canadians?
Disappointing?
Yeah, disappointing for the girls there.
But of course, they do have an Olympic medal in their room in the Olympic Village or wherever they choose to keep it from the synchronized event.
And they dived, well, awesomely well in that event.
A highly run contest, as you would imagine.
And they ended up with an Olympic bronze and couldn't quite raise their game here in the final.
All ladies faltering, but some more than others.
And the Canadians just finishing
at the bottom of the pack.
Just looking at the sequence of dives for Chen, 85, 84, 86, slightly less, slightly being the operative word, 79.2 at 86.
What a sequence of dives though.
She never got to the 90s, and she never had a 10, sadly, which I think would have underlined that performance.
But how consistent is that?
Well, that's the name of the game, isn't it?
And she is a cut above the rest, if you just look at that.
Lowest scoring dive of 79.
and then everything in the 80s and with the degree of difficulty she's using she's maxing out isn't she so nines pretty much across the board on most of her dives makes her untouchable.
What an absolute champion to retain her Olympic title and she's only 19.
How can you have two Olympic titles when you're 19?
Wow and what about Broban who who dropped will not drop but certainly was well below what it should have been for round four.
No you're right opening dive was weak um for her low degree of difficulty 60 that could have been more and dive number four which was her
what was it her back three and a half that was the one that was the big dive probably her bogey dive and she did underperform certainly on that dive but it didn't affect the result look at that she was clearly in bronze by six points yeah clearly from bronze i mean silver ahead of bronze by six points
on by a massive margin but it was what she needed and well that's kind of the final we needed because I think we we often a bit lackluster a bit lukewarm after the prelims last night.
Semifinals didn't really get us out of our seats and on the edge of them this morning but
Just because it was so competitive and so close, you really didn't know which way it was going to go.
You knew the gold pretty much from the outset.
I don't think there was ever going to be much question about that.
But it's really exciting when you're seeing two countries, or in this case five or six countries, all going for the bronze and silver medals.
Yeah, it's like the swimming race all coming in in a line.
You never really know who's going to get it until the touch.
But obviously the drama here in the diving pool because it is like for like, dive for dive.
Most of the girls then opting to decide an hour before the competition the dives need to be submitted to the officials and so we know what's coming up.
So it's a game of tactics and by some of them very well played.
So if you have just joined us, just a recap.
We'll have the medal ceremony for you very shortly.
But Chen Ruolin of China, 19 years of age, has retained her title from Beijing, the world champion from last year in Shanghai, in great style.
She won it by 56 points in the end, or very nearly, give or take a couple of percentage points.
of Australia.
Brittany Brobin, sixteen years of age.
The big surprise.
Although actually after the semi is not quite such a surprise.
We kind of almost marked your card on her doing roll tonight.
Uh winning her silver medal by seven points and but one stage we thought, ah, she's giving herself a bit too much to do.
Sixty-four in dive number three and she seemed to have let it slip but then she
and pulls herself right up the standings.
So Minister Wu not going to be her day by just over a point one point one zero in the end.
Coulter Nova had it in her hands and just couldn't I mean she was consistent throughout but just didn't have that big dive
in the 80s to lift her up there.
Espinosa Sanchez was quite fortunate to make the semis anyway improved in the semi-final and certainly improved in the final as well but again wasn't quite enough for her to get there.
Kristen Sturr, she might be a very surprised medalist at one stage but everybody else upped their game and Bakke in eighth place right at the bottom.
In case you're wondering well I've only heard about one Chinese Hu Yudan
just never got going early on and all of a sudden from out of absolutely nowhere to immaculate dives and we just didn't see that coming.
No great word well we've seen it in training she was world silver medalist last year in Shanghai and a performance out there was outstanding she in fact pushed Chen so if you remember that contest it was very closely run and since we've seen her here in prelims and semis who you've done has been way off the pace first three rounds here she was way off the pace and then
She comes out with the highest scoring dive of the competition at 89 points for a back three and a half, which is 3.3 degree of difficulty.
And then she backs it right up with a back two and a half, one and a half twist for 86.4.
And then she puts herself right back up in contention and ends up in fifth position.
Well, she missed out on the medal by two points.
Two points, 349 against 351.
So that's how close it was.
So no, you ended up in ninth, I beg your pardon, but she went all the way up there.
Yeah.
Right, we are ready to go.
The divers are in a position to be paraded on poolside.
I'm sure there's a lot of tears and a lot of emotion and a lot of excitement out there.
Probably not for the victor because she's done it so many times before.
It's pretty much routine for Chen Ruolin.
But for the others, for Broban, first time, for Pam, who was involved in the Synchro last week, so she got a flavor of this building and the competition in the pool in the synchronized event last week.
She has picked up a bronze medal, but that's a lineup we weren't really expecting when the competition got underway.
It is another goal for China.
They've only missed out so far on the men's three meter individual.
All the other goals have gone to China.
And there's a nice bonus bronze for
And he's delighted.
And I think Chen will break open a smile shortly.
And I know we'll definitely see one from Brittany Broban who is just taking it all in, looking around and looking at the crowd and wanting to suck up every little fiber of what is happening here to her.
probably in reality will go to bed tonight, say, I'll wake up.
I will have been dreaming but you haven't.
It's true.
It's real and it's happening right now to the sixteen year old from Australia.
Here comes the presentation party.
which is
Here comes the medal ceremony and the medal presentations.
First of all, to the 19-year-old from Malaysia, Pandela Pang.
359.20, the marks for the Malaysian.
And she's absolutely thrilled to get that bronze.
Yeah.
Enjoy it.
Make the most of it.
It's been a hard fought competition.
And some big names fell by the wayside here.
Not she.
Big medals, aren't they?
Are we going to see tears?
Are we going to see a smile?
What are we going to see from Brittany Brobin?
Yeah, it's a big smile.
Looks to the sizeable Australian contingent.
Looks towards her teammates.
Looks at that chunky bit of metal work.
I might say silverware.
Of course it is a silver medal.
So it is silverware in those terms.
And they're delighted.
Waterworks here in the start amongst the family and friends though.
Even though she can keep it together.
But another absolutely impeccable day at the office.
This is what she calls her office, Chen Ruolin.
And the Chinese tend to do this.
They go and do a little route march around the medal platform, shaking the hands of the two bronze and silver medalists.
And first real emotional reaction from Chen Ruolin.
This is a chunky bit of metal work around her neck.
She receives a bouquet of flowers.
Olympic champion, 2008.
Olympic champion, 2012.
She's done it again.
And world champion as well.
The unbeatable, as things stand, Chen Ruolin with gold for China in the women's 10-meter platform final.
And once again, the national anthem of China will ring out around the Aquatic Center.
you
Large proportion of the Aquatic Centre crowd have stayed behind to acknowledge a thrilling competition, certainly for the silver and the bronze and the imperious gold medallist who is Chen Ruolin.
So the women have done their stuff in 23 hours or less.
It'll be the men's turn.
Men's 10 meter platform final.
We'll have more entrance to that than we will have any competition here in the diving pool.
Leon Taylor, of course, competed at the Olympics in 2000 and 2004 in that event.
And 1996 as well.
I don't want to make you sound too old, so I'm just going to mention the ones that people can remember.
We're talking about colour television here, not black and white.
What are you thinking?
What are you hoping?
What are you expecting?
Well it's a marathon, 32 boys going head to head, cut to 18 and they've got to get up early the next morning.
We've seen this program and it is tough because the men's final is actually going to be a little bit later on Saturday night, 8.30pm local time.
So it's who can hold their body together, who can hold their nerve and who can dive most consistently because I would dare to say the level is going to be through the roof.
I need to save my voice, I need to save my energy and I cannot wait to bring the Blue Ribbon event to you.
Some amazing dives ahead still to finish off and I would like to predict lots and lots of perfect scores coming, maybe not so much in the preliminaries but semi-final and final.
I'm pretty sure the judges will be inputting at least one or two perfect 10s.
Maybe even more than that.
Worth tuning in for wherever you are in the world.
Please come and join us.
All right.
So check your times for Friday evening.
It will be UK time at 1900 BST.
The preliminaries for the men's and then the semifinal will be on Saturday morning local time at 10 o'clock.
Obviously, sort out your London reference points in terms of your time differential, because you do not want to be missing the prelims on Friday, the semifinal, and certainly the final on Saturday night at 7.30 local time.
Thank you for joining us for the Women's 10m platform.
We lived up to all the expectations and a few surprises along the way, not with the winner
but with the silver and the bronze medal.
From Leon Taylor and myself, Bob Ballard, thank you for joining us at the Aquatic Center.
We'll be back for the final event of the diving competition in about 23 hours from now.
Till then, goodbye.
Thank you very much.
One, two, three, four.
Thank you for joining us today.